Welcome everyone to a uh a video
discussion about preaching with Zach
Eswine. Uh I'm Andy Patton with the
Alliance for Mission and Renewal. Uh we
wanted today to uh basically squeeze all
the preaching wisdom out of Zach Eswine
that we can fit into an hour. So that is
what's about to happen. Uh if you don't
know Zach, he is a preacher at Riverside
Church in St. Louis, Missouri. He's the
author of numerous books including The
Imperfect Pastor and most recently Wiser
with Jesus and he heads Sage
Christianity. And Zach, you can tell us
about uh fill in any more of those
details that that you want. Um but I am
just going to pass it over to Zach and
we will hear from him. And then there
there's an audience in this Zoom call
and the second half of what we're all
about to experience is just it's going
to be a conversation uh about preaching.
So, Zach, over to you.
>> Uh thanks so much Andy and thanks
everybody for uh joining in today and um
I'm so glad to have this conversation.
If I was to sort of name the
conversation uh as I'm thinking of it,
uh I would I would say something like
this. Um, I wrote a book some years ago
called Preaching to a Post Everything
World. What would I say differently now,
uh, these years later? And I'm coming at
that question. I'm I've been, uh, pastor
at Riverside Church in St. St. Louis for
the last 17 years. Um, the location that
I'm in is a highly progressive one. uh
culturally, ideologically, most folks
who come to know Jesus uh where I'm
located are coming from the left as it
were uh rather than from other places.
And so it's been an ongoing um
invitation to learn to communicate to
folks. And uh where I serve uh is a a
politically purple congregation that is
uh in our polarized political landscape.
um uh folks uh come from all across that
landscape and um keep hanging in there
together with Jesus and our
congregation. And so, uh, thinking
through that political landscape,
thinking through COVID, uh, thinking
through the economic realities, thinking
through the racial, uh, realities,
thinking through mass shootings,
globalization, all those things that
take place over the last several years
as a pastor, uh, someone trying to stand
up publicly and communicate Jesus in
that kind of context. Um, here's a few
things I've been um thinking through and
that's been helping me grow. But I have
a lot to learn. Uh, I'm eager to learn
from you. Uh, as I mentioned, I I'm
preaching Sunday. Uh, starting a series
on Job. I've never preached through the
s uh job before. And um, so I'm I'm just
in it with you. Uh so what what might I
say differently um or in a in a more
complete way today if I were saying it?
The first thing I would say is wisdom.
I'm I'm looking for wisdom
and I'm thinking through that uh as best
I can from a biblical point of view. So
I'm going to think about Jesus as our
prophet, priest and king and also as the
one greater than Solomon. Um and so one
way to think of that is that uh in his
offices of prophet, priest and king, our
lord uh you know execututeth those
offices he doth execute those offices
wisely. That's what I'd like to suggest.
And so that's meaning uh several things
but a couple of things for today would
be this. Number one, uh when I taught
preaching uh earlier in earlier years,
uh I passed on what I was taught which
was a twomude view of preaching, what is
true and what to do, uh indicative
imperative. But biblically when we
encounter the communicators within the
scripture itself, the way God
communicates to us, when we see the
communication of the of the prophets,
the biblically wise, our Lord Jesus
himself, we we begin to realize there
are at least five moods that the Lord
uses to communicate to us what is and
what to do for sure. Not less than that,
um just more than that. Um there's also
the interrogative mood asking questions
uh that are actual questions
uh and willingness to wait with time and
space uh for a question to be worked
out. Um there's also the subjunctive
mood which is uh setting whatif
scenarios in front of us. Uh like our
lord when he tells us a parable, he sets
at least two paths in front of us. We're
invited to imagine what happens if we
take either path and to work that out in
our imagination. Or he might tell uh
tell us a a a proverb, you know, foxes
have dens and birds have nests, but the
son of man has nowhere to lay his head.
And then he's content to be quiet and
let us sort that out. Um he's very
willing to say, "He who has ears, let
him hear." And then walk away and let
what he just said sit with us. So that's
a subjunctive mood where things aren't
aren't um tied up in a bow very quickly.
And then there's an optitive mood which
is uh desire, the mood of desire. Uh
Jerusalem, Jerusalem, how I would have
gathered you as a hen gathers her
chicks. Um but you would not. It's an
expression of longing which we see often
in Job or the Psalms or Ecclesiastes on
the lips of our Lord himself. And so
when we think about those moods in a
message, um I wrote a little chapter and
sent it to us as a group and you could
imagine um 10 p.m. on a the edge of a
bed, a a daughter comes in uh to mom and
dad uh and and s and is trying to talk
about something and says she's thinking
about trying witchcraft
and um if the mom and the dad only have
a two mood toolbox, if they've only been
mentored by their preachers to do what
is true and what to do, they're going to
assume without knowing it a prophetic
paradigm. And on the basis of that
prophetic paradigm, they're going to
bring two moods to that uh young girl on
the edge of the bed. What is true and
what to do? They might even bring a
posture of anger to it. Not in my house.
And things like that.
But if they know they can ask questions,
then they can slow down and they can ask
a question like, "What is it about
witchcraft that seems attractive to
you?" Because after all, they're
recognizing, wow, their daughter has
just done what they've prayed years for.
She's just come to them with the deepest
questions of her heart and she's risking
it with them. They ask a question, "What
attracts you?" And then she says
something like, "I'm just so troubled by
the pain in the world. My friends are
hurting. The world is hurting. It seems
like we need a power that's more than
human to be able to handle it."
So I was just thinking maybe I should
look into witchcraft.
Some of my friends are. And at that
point the parents can feel somewhat
relieved.
Uh the daughter's not bringing to them a
picture of uh tarot cards and pointy
hats and a mixture of some kind of
Satanism. And uh she has compassion for
the plight of people and she's trying to
find a source greater than human to
address it. And this is a massive
softball [laughter]
offered right to mom and dad who if if
they would have not paused to ask a
question, if they would have gone right
to what is true, what to do? Witchcraft
is a sin. That's what is true. Here's
what you do. Repent. If they had done
that, they would have uh
mischaracterized and misrepresented
where she was actually coming from. they
would have shut the conversation down
and uh she would have gone back into her
room perhaps with tears feeling unheard
and uh it might take another 20 years
for them to repair that. Uh but the
interrogative mood uh reminds us that we
can slow down, be quick to quick listen,
slow to speak, slow to vent anger, we
can ask a question. You can imagine um
then uh how those five moods might begin
to reshape the way we approach a sermon
as well as parenting or friendship or
pastoral care. A second thing is that
those five moods assume three voices
rather than two uh rather than one. So
um the Lord speaks to us in his word
prophetically by means of a prophet.
Yeah. But also through priests and also
through sages um and uh their
relationship to the king. If I had time,
I'd love to flesh that out for you. But
I would just say that if you um think
about um a biblical text, say in the
book of Proverbs, and you look at how
the sages talk about say drunkenness or
alcohol, and then you compare that with
how a prophet would talk about alcohol
and its uses or how a priest
talks about alcohol and its uses, you
begin to get a sense that the sage is a
person who speaks from inside the
experience. as if they understand why
it's a temptation, as if they know
firsthand what it's like. And from
inside of it, they bring all five moods
to bear, inviting the person to think
about it and give them time to think
about it. And um that that kind of um
those voices, we don't want less than
a pro prophetic paradigm. It's just
there's more in scripture. Finally, I've
hinted at it. quick to listen, slow to
speak, slow to anger. Uh we could be um
slow to listen and quick to speak and
quick to anger. So, we're going to speed
up
and shut something down. Uh we could
also be uh slow to listen, slow to
speak, and quick to anger. So, we're
going to shut down and be passive
uh with our intensity.
Um but uh you can imagine on the edge of
the bed if those parents have five moves
not two three voices not one and instead
of shutting down or speeding up they can
remain present quick to listen slow to
speak slow to anger you can imagine uh
not a promise or guarantee that that
situation's going to work out but
suddenly those parents have a lot of
biblical resources to draw upon to give
their daughter every chance of
experiencing the posture, the heart, and
the way of Jesus in meeting her and her
longing for compassion and for help.
There's a lot to say there, but uh
that's uh uh something I would flesh out
much more um if I was uh talking about
preaching today than maybe I would have
a decade ago.
One other sort of line of inquiry
and very similar would be this. If
someone were to ask me what is
preaching, you know, how do you approach
preaching today? I'm going to talk about
those moods, those voices, that posture
from a wisdom angle.
But then I'm going to take a sort of
summary view and just say in summary,
it's like this. Think of our Lord Jesus
in the sermon on the mount when he had
that repeated phrase. Um,
uh, you have heard it said, but I say to
you,
uh, let's just think about all the
components that are there. First,
there's an it. You have heard it said.
So, as you walk through that sermon, the
Lord Jesus makes very clear what
subjects he's talking about. Uh we would
think of the it with words like the
proposition, the big idea, the thesis,
the subject, the it, the thing we're
going to talk about. You've heard it
said.
Uh but then there's you've heard said.
You've heard said. And our Lord Jesus is
going to quote how the culture is
talking about the it he's about to
address.
Um people have experienced
our proposition, our big idea, uh
before. They have conceptions and
misconceptions about it. Um they're not
a clean slate when they come to the
thing we're talking about. So it you've
heard said, you've heard said takes into
account what people hear said
regarding the subject we're about to
address.
Then there's but you have heard said but
there's the the problem of the either
there's something completely wrong with
what people are hearing said about the
it we're about to talk about or uh there
are things to commend but sensing pieces
and um Jesus as you know uh in commends
offends and invites
And uh he's an equal opportunity
commener, offender, and inviter. And so
um you have heard said, "But
as we if we had time, we could walk
through I'd give you several examples.
You might think of them yourself as you
begin to think about the gospels where
the Lord Jesus commends something but
then exposes something that's missing."
So, like he'll say to uh near the end of
Matthew there where he's about to begin
his prophetic mantle of woes uh coming
down there, he'll say uh uh um listen to
what the Pharisees say, but don't do
what they do.
Uh he's commending something about them,
but then he's exposing a problem with
them. or think about uh not not with a
sort of um uh covenantal church life,
but think about um um life outside of
that with other than Christian people as
we would say it today when Jesus uh
speaks to his disciples and they're
thinking about who's the greatest and um
he tells us that the Gentiles
uh lord over others and in that spot
Jesus doesn't commend anything. He
plainly says it will not be so among
you. They're completely off. Uh they're
they're thinking about this topic of
leadership as it were and they're
completely off in the way they think of
it. And so there's an it that people
have heard talked about and then there
is a problem either fully or partially
with what they've heard said.
And then I say to you, there's the
Christ centeredness, the Christ uh um
cal Christ calibrated, Christ centered,
cra Christ drenched, Christ oriented,
whatever you want to call it, right?
There's the orbit around the authority
of Jesus
in light of the thing we're talking
about and the problems we're addressing.
And then finally, how do we know that
any of these moves uh are are happening?
Well, we're reading it in the Bible.
Matthew chapter 5 verse through chapter
7, the scripture is letting us know that
this is what took place. So, you could u
sort of a final thought here to prompt
our conversation. You you could imagine
that as a an evaluation, evaluative
help. It's incomplete, but it's
substantial an evaluative help for us.
Um, some of us uh might have a very
clear it. You know, we're very clear
about what we're talking about. Uh,
we've named a problem. Well, we're
pointing us to Jesus from the scripture.
But people go away feeling like uh we're
not talking about their real life
because uh they don't hear what they
hear said in our messages and how
they're to interact with it. You can
imagine on the flip side, right? Someone
who very well uh connects with what
people here said uh and point us to
Jesus. Uh but we have no idea where in
the scripture we are, how we got here
from the scripture, and we're not quite
sure if what's been said is biblical uh
because it's not anchored for us um in
the in the scripture. So you you and I
could help think about ourselves. I
mean, for me, it could be any given
week. Uh um last week compared to this
week and then the next week because
Sunday's always coming and the reality
of what that's like in the midst of a
week of family and pastoral care and
everything else. But could you step back
and say, "Will people know what we're
talking about?
Am I making any connection to how the
culture talks about this? Am I engaging
the disconnect or the missing piece? um
the tension point between our uh what's
said and what Jesus would say. I'm a
hallowing Jesus exalting him and his
authority appropriately from the
scripture and am is it from the
scripture that I'm doing these things.
How am I doing on that? Uh incomplete
but substantial help in that way. So
stepping back those are two sort of
environments of conversation that I'm
exploring these days and what there's a
lot more to say but uh thinking through
five moods uh rather than two three
voices rather than one a posture of
wisdom uh wisdom from above rather than
shutting down or speeding up. And behind
all of that is this what are we talking
about? What's the culture saying about
it? How does that compare in contrast
with Jesus and what he's saying about
it? And and how would I know that in
light of the scripture
that's very brief uh and there's a lot
in there, but I hope there's enough
there to sort of prompt prompt our
conversation together. And I'm I'm eager
to learn from you because like I said,
um I'm in it with you and uh learning as
well.
>> Thank you so much, Zach. You've you've
set the table for us. Uh, one of the
things I'd like to do now is, um, lead
us into a conversation. There's probably
15 people on this call or so, and
they're here because they have
questions. Um, so I I want to provide
some time for a chat. I If you have
questions uh, as as we talk, feel free
to unmute yourself. I'll spotlight you
on screen. Um, it can be a bit messy and
that's fine. you if you've got something
to say, you can you can jump in. Uh,
Zach, I wonder if I can kick us off with
a question.
uh you've you've given us these moods
and these voices and one of the things
as you were talking that I was thinking
about is
um there's this reality we we have an
unchanging book full of wisdom and yet
we're trying to apply that wisdom to a a
specific congregation in a specific time
and place in the midst of a larger
culture uh that is always changing. So
can you give us any insight on how to
how to approach
I don't know if current events is the
right way to say it but h how to bring
life presents us with all kinds of
questions and there are many people who
would offer answers to those questions
many voices and we come to church and
the preacher stands up opens the word
and applies it in in various ways and I
preachers shouldn't be just another
pundit. Uh but also we shouldn't steer
clear because that's of current events
because that's where people's lives are.
>> So can you can you guide us into that
tension of how to how to apply the the
unchanging word to a very changing
culture?
>> Well, that's such a that's the question
for so many of us, isn't it? Um,
and uh, first of all, I think through
trial and error, you know, we're we're
going to try and uh, we'll take some
criticisms here and there uh, from
people who don't know what it's like to
stand up publicly and try to speak to
the actual things that are going on uh,
from a as if we're a follower of Jesus.
But we're going to we're going to make
mistakes, but we're going to we're going
to keep keep at it together. Uh, keep
keep learning together. And I I think
one of the things that I'm learning is
which might sound so trit but I mean it
is sincerely is uh the distinctiveness
of Jesus is where we begin. This is um
the distinctiveness of Jesus. And so um
in in essence I'll put it this way.
There's nothing there's nothing new
under the sun. uh we don't have a
onetoone correspondence with the ancient
neareastern world or the Roman world but
um Yahweh and um the God who loved us
and sent his son Jesus is distinctive
all the way through uh whether we're in
the Old Testament in ancient Neareastern
context with Baal and Marduk and uh the
gods and goddesses there or if we're in
uh the Roman world in the first century
So let's think about the Roman world in
the first century very briefly. Uh the
the Pharisees said we have to go back in
order to get close to God. We we've got
to recover our nation. We've got to go
back to what we once were uh in order to
be ready for God. The Sadducees were
saying no. These are educated elites as
you know and they're saying we've got to
go forward. We can't go back. We've got
to go forward. And then you have the
Essins who are saying no. we've got to
withdraw. We've just got to get out of
all of this. And then of course, you
know, you have the Herodians who are
saying, "No, we've got to politically
negotiate our interests in order to get
our nation the way it we we need it to
be with God." And then, of course, you
have the zealots who are saying, "No, in
the name of God, we need to take up
weapons and physically fight people in
order to have our nation back for
itself." Now the problem with the the
help there is not a onetoone
correspondence but I have to say it
there's a lot of resonance with there we
humanity really only has about four or
five options that it continued returns
to when it's trying to address the
problems of its culture. Um the there is
nothing new under the sun. uh the wise
learned this. And so
uh the problem that um Jesus, our Lord,
had
was that he did not follow any of those
paths.
He disrupted each one of those paths.
And um
that's where that's where I'd want to
begin talking together if we had another
several hours together. week.
Let's begin with the distinctiveness of
Jesus.
What makes him distinctive within the
voices that he was dealing with that
resonate with the voices we're dealing
with? And if we can follow him in that
distinctiveness,
um we're going to sound more like him.
Uh and it's and it's going to be
disorienting and disruptive
to these other postures, but it it will
give us the hope um to see the
difference. And so that we're entering
and and that is a check on our own heart
in community that we're not just
following our we're not just taking up
the talking points of the Pharisees or
the we're not saying we got to go back.
We got to go forward. We got to get out.
We got to fight. We got to politically
maneuver. At that point, we sound no
different than anybody of any time and
place.
A distinctive Jesus voice is where we
need help. And uh that's what I'd want
to pursue together. That's a start.
>> Yeah, that's a good start.
Does anyone want to pick up this thread
or introduce another
question burning on your mind?
>> I'll go and uh describe one real quick.
Uh Mike Palumbo. Um so in the different
moods that we uh see here that you
mentioned, the interrogative mood, the
subjunctive optative mood, is there are
there any kind of key clues that we're
looking for as we're studying texts to
discern which mood would be the most
effective to use in the preaching
sermon? Uh or is this something where we
should think about bringing in different
angles throughout uh a sermon? you know,
bringing a interrogative angle or
optative angle. Uh, so how how do we
discern which angle might be most
effective or useful when preaching a
given text?
>> That's a great question. There's a lot
to say there, but uh maybe a brief place
to begin uh is to think about who who
our audience is
in comparison and contrast with the
audience of the text we're preaching.
And so one example would be this. Let's
say we're preaching Galatians 1. You
know, we're going through Galatians.
Galatians 1, who has bewitched you? You
know, there's interrogative, right? But
this there's heat behind this
interrogative, right? This is this isn't
uh the the sage saying who has woe. This
is a prophetic approach of who has
bewitched you foolish. Galatians. Um and
then he's you know if anyone preaches to
you something other than what we've
preached uh and then he's declaring
judgment right now let's imagine for to
make this simple that I'm the the
assisted living Bible study group wanted
to go through Galatians and um I just
read this text and there's 88year-old
and 92 year old and 707 year old widows
there's Betty right there and and Betty
I have to ask myself, um, is Betty a
Judaizer?
Is 88-year-old widowed Betty the the
wife of an OPC pastor all those years?
Is she a Judaizer? Because that's who
Paul's addressing.
Maybe she is, [laughter] you know, but I
I'm not going to assume that until I get
to know Betty. Uh, and so I'm going to
take a I I'm going to point out Paul's
prophetic posture,
but I'm not going to do it as if Betty
needs my prophetic woe on her. So, what
I'm going to do is say I'm going to use
wisdom moods like we just talked about.
Something like I'm going to read that
and I'm going to say, "Wow, that's
pretty intense, isn't it?" Paul seems to
be really bothered. uh he's speaking
really straightforwardly.
Uh what's that feel like to you? H how
are you experiencing that? You know, and
then I'm going to say u well what is it
that he's addressing? Well, these are
people who are saying that you need
Jesus plus something else. And they're
confusing earnest followers of Jesus.
They're making it hard. And you know
what? It's already hard to be a
Christian in the Roman Empire. And these
church people are going along and
they're making it harder. And so what's
that like to realize that Paul can get
really feisty to defend Christians who
are being misled and misused? Could what
kind of hope that might that give you in
your own life if if someone's coming
along and mistreating you to know that
that the Lord's servant like the Apostle
Paul would want to defend you with the
gospel? We might talk about that. But I
still have in my mind we need to feel
the force of the prophetic declaration
here. Right. Uh and so so now I'm going
to say now let's imagine that I'm going
into a subjunctive mood here. Now let's
imagine that we find ourselves in this
position that we're saying Jesus yes but
we also have to do all these other
things.
What's it like to realize that the Lord,
God himself, the one of grace and mercy
to you, would speak this directly to you
to wake you up? Could you ever imagine
the Lord speaking that directly to you
out of love to shake you out of this?
What would that be like? Now, with
Betty, we're thinking about the impact
of a prophetic woe. We've imagined
oursel in that position. And I'm not
saying we're there, but what if we found
ourselves there? This is what we would
expect from God. And this isn't mean on
God's part. This is his love for us. So
there's an anecdote. Uh maybe there's
enough in that scene to start a movement
in the direction of your awesome
question. Yeah.
Thank you.
>> Yeah. What does this mean for structure?
Like would you Would
you change I'm thinking of if you're
either if it's inductive or deductive
would you change a structure or are
these things that you're thinking okay I
have this structure but all are these
are the um these are the things that are
shaping my tone and posture as I walk
through this or are you like change the
whole structure base it all on which
voice or mood
>> that's a great question. If I'm just if
I'm in a beginning preaching or
communication course, I'm um
I'm just going to, you know, continue
with explain, illustrate, apply, you
know, uh that's where we're going to
start. Uh what um so this what I'm
talking about now would be uh year
three. you know, it it would be once
we've established our
our basic uh uh capacity to to
understand what a text is saying and to
try to communicate that text. Um then
I'm going to begin to introduce these
things and um what that will do for us
is number one that becomes its
uh it you've heard said but I say to you
becomes its own structure. So that can
be its own structure for a particular
message that that's not going to be
helpful on certain texts of scripture.
Um but it can be helpful on some and um
that adds a new structure. Sometimes I
will follow this structure. Um if I'm
addressing um particularly if I'm dress
addressing um non you know a
non-Christian audience. I'm I'm at a I
have 20 minutes to speak on a college
campus and then there's going to be Q&A.
Uh I will use this structure. Um or uh
there are times I will use this
structure in the wisdom literature
itself and I recognize there's some
debate about whether there's actual
wisdom literature etc. But in those
books we t typically associate it. I I
might use that as its own structure. And
there are times when I feel stuck.
I'm I'm in an induct I'm in a narrative.
I'm gonna use an inductive structure,
but I feel stuck. I might step back and
say, "Okay, what's the it
am I checking in with what people are
saying about it? How would they relate
to this narrative?" You know, just as a
way uh to help me step back in um to
that structure.
And so, um, what at the end of the day,
it can be its own structure. That's what
I've said. But now, it can also be a way
of evaluating, helping me think about
the structure I'm already using, a
deductive or an inductive structure. Um,
and and thinking about in an evaluative
way, am I clear about what I'm talking
about? Am I engaging how culture
interacts with this? Am I commending,
offending, inviting,
you know, the the but you know here and
and how am I relating this to Christ and
am I doing this in a uh a biblically
appropriate way? Um and then am I clear
with folks where I'm at in scripture? So
if it's not its own structure, it
becomes a way of evaluating the
structure I'm using and helping me
remember um certain of these things.
Chris, do you want to follow up on any
of that?
>> No, just that it's really helpful and we
could use like three more hours of all
the examples. [laughter]
>> Good. Zach, you should write all this
down in a book somewhere.
>> I I need to try to do that. [laughter]
>> Um, thanks Zach for all this. This is
super helpful. Um, one thing that you've
mentioned a number of times in our
conversation so far is um, the culture,
addressing it, understanding it. Um, one
thing I'm finding in pastoral ministry
is it's really difficult to discern what
the culture is, uh, as our people are
very different and are shaped and formed
by different things. Just curious from
your part how you gauge and understand
whatever the culture is that you're
trying to speak to. uh whether that's
spending time with your people, reading
articles online or whatever whatever
rhythms you have uh to sort of
understand the culture you're speaking
into because that's just a really
complicated question in general. So any
wisdom would be helpful on that.
>> Yeah, I so appreciate that you added the
the s to the word culture. cultures
um uh because that slows us way down uh
back into a humble posture of listening
and having to daily pay attention uh
which is a wisdom posture.
Um I I think this question when when um
when someone thinks about culture they
can uh a young a young preacher or
communicator teacher Bible teacher Bible
say they can think they need to uh that
means they got to read the New York
Times. um that means they have to make
sure they've watched the latest movies,
uh things like that.
Those things can be helpful um and they
have a place. But but I would say
pastorally,
um our understanding our culture begins
locally right where we're at. And that
means the local congregation in which
we're rooted. Now, for those of us who
speak uh in itinerant ways, we're on
different cultural things. there's more
to say about that, but but for any of us
in local work, that's that's really
where it all is. Um, so that we're and
so that means what you've already hinted
at, we're listening to the people that
we talk to, how they interact with what
we're saying, what they don't get, what
what they're missing, what they didn't
understand,
um, being willing. It's not easy, but
receiving that kind of feedback, paying
attention to who they're listening to.
Um, where are they getting this, you
know, so I, you know, I wouldn't have
read I I'm, you know, I may not have
read Percy Jackson and the Olympians on
my own, but I have a lot of folks, a lot
of young people in our congregation who
have have read that or are watching the
show.
Um, and so I I uh want to know um what
that is. Well, it turns out what a
helpful thing not only for our
congregation but culturally because it's
also giving echoes of this resurgence of
old paganisms in our culture and things
like that. But
um what are people listening to that
we're serving? Um and then uh what what
community am I in?
uh and what it pays attention to, what
its sensibilities are. So, if I was in
um you know, if I was in St. Charles,
uh it it'd be very different. It's only
a half hour drive from where I'm at, but
it's very different place than Webster
Groves. And so if I'm reading larger
material in Webster Groves, I'm reading
The New Yorker. I'm reading The
Atlantic. I'm reading Publishers Weekly.
Uh because um the influence that the
influential ways of thought
uh more resonate from those cultural
spaces in Webster Groves. Um, and I uh
am trying to learn the background, the
background beliefs, the invisible
beliefs, you know, as Tim Keller would
would have reminded us, the background
uh assumptions that people are bringing
in my culture. And so I'm starting the
people I listen to, the Webster,
Kirkwood Times,
uh, St. those post dispatch on into a
more centrist leftoriented
type of uh periodical. If I'm in St.
Charles, um I'm I'm I'm probably getting
to a different place
uh because my starting place is going to
have to be different to get a hearing.
And here's one here's a final example.
uh if I'm uh there's a let's say I'm
going to uh
commend offend and invite both the right
and the left in one message which often
happens at where I serve
um
if I'm in St. Charles, just to keep if
I'm in a conservative a more
conservative leaning place,
uh, and, uh, and I have 8020, you know,
conservativeleaning, right? 80% 20% of
the congregation, 70% 30%. Um, I'm going
to start with the gospel critique
of a liberal cultural assumption. I'm
going to start there.
Um so that uh the folks who are coming
from the cultural the conservative
cultural space hear me say yes I know I
agree with you
right
u and then then I'm coming [laughter]
for the gospel challenge that might come
into the conservative space um which is
conflating conservatism with
Christianity and doesn't realize it. But
in Webster Groves, in my local congre
congregation, I always start if if
there's this kind of double critique, I
always start with the gospel criti
critique of the more conservative
because of the same reason. Uh that
that's where the the church is in the
churches that I the congregation I'm
serving. That's where the skepticisms
come from. I'm going to let them know I
see the gospel critique of this right
here from the text.
On occasion, I've even said I'll even
say no. I'm about to uh show the
distinctiveness of Jesus. He's going to
press in on us right here. And as we do
that, some of you are going to say,
"Yes, I just want you to know in about
seven minutes, I'm coming your way." you
know
uh so
um that's a sort of an outworking of
knowing our local our local place
otherwise if I only otherwise if I only
if I only critique what the conservative
would critique
then I continue the notion the mistaken
notion that conservatism the political
ideology of conservatism is synonymous
with the gospel. So I I have to be able
to do both and vice versa. Um and if I
don't do that, I'm also I'm fmenting an
us versus them scenario
uh which works against all of us have
sinned and fallen short of the glory of
God and moves us in the direction of
that parable Jesus said about the guy
who prayed in the temple saying I thank
you God I'm not like other people. So we
want to stay in that that equal
opportunity commending offending
inviting situation. But I think that's
we best have that if we start by
listening to our local congregation and
our local people before we think we have
to jump to what say to what Tim Keller
read. Um, we we remember we learn from
what he so well embodied for us, but we
but Webster Groves isn't Manhattan and I
need to remember that.
>> Yeah,
>> that's super helpful. Thanks, Zach.
>> Yeah, thanks for that,
>> Zach. We have a few other questions I
want to get to, but um there's there's
one that I really want to hit before we
move on. Uh it's currently September
2025.
Uh the the world is changing. It's
changed a lot in the past three years. I
I was just having a conversation with a
friend who's who works in AI and he said
the comment [clears throat] we we're
going to look back on chat GBT like uh
the old days of dialup America online
soon.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh so things are changing. It's changing
so fast. uh the
models are it's kind of an alphabet soup
of new models appearing all the time and
their capabilities are increasing so
quickly. Uh and no one really knows what
where it's all going or what what has
already changed. Um so we're
we should probably talk a little bit
about what that looks like. what is the
impact of AI on um the work of a
preacher and also anyone who's trying to
communicate about the gospel into um
people who's who also don't know what to
do with AI but are interested or afraid
of it. Uh can you speak to that if if
you're up for it? [clears throat] Yes,
I'm I'm in the boat with all of us
learning like everybody else uh in this
grand experiment. Uh
uh I I think caution is is is good. Uh
wisdom uh a recognition that
uh good things can be used for bad ends.
Uh and so and I think the wisdom of
nuance
uh we can commend um the help that this
is medically to doctors and nurses
uh while at the same time recognizing um
you know a recent article I forget if
it's a the Atlantic or the New Yorker
but talking about how chat GPT led
someone through a satanic ritual uh and
taught them how to kill someone. Um and
so I think we have to be very uh astute
to
uh what we can commend and what and what
we're wise to. Second thing is a re a
reminder that uh that AI depends upon
human knowledge and human input. And so
I don't understand all these things but
I know that uh the generative generative
nature of AI is uh is building and
creating synthesizing on the basis of
what we've put into it. And so that
means that we also have to recognize the
potential for our own biases uh our own
missteps our own mistakes in the
knowledge that it's drawing upon.
Uh
and so um the d the the the temptation
for any artist, any any teacher,
preacher, uh is going to be to use um
the capability
to bypass our own creativity.
And um I think time is going to show us
what that does to our brain, to our
soul.
um studies, early studies are already
begun, MIT has a study recently
beginning to start to demonstrate the
effect of bypassing creativity in our
use of AI and what it's doing to us. I
think um I trust that that'll be similar
to this grand experience of experiment
of my generation with my older kids uh
smartphones um and now all the things we
know about smartphones uh and a
generation that's pushing back on the
use of smart I trust that there will be
something like that uh with this
practically where it come uh I should
say um uh practically where that comes
down to is I think I'm landing where
most where solid people are and where
chat GPT
lands right now. If you ask chat GPD,
which I did uh for this talk, uh uh
what what should uh how do I put it?
It's something like um why should a a
Christian preacher not rely on chat GPT?
Or ask the question, what are the pros
and cons of a Christian preacher relying
on chat GPT for a sermon? And uh it was
a surprisingly
uh good answer which uh was uh we should
not use it to bypass our creativity. We
shouldn't use it uh to uh plagiarize. Uh
we shouldn't use it to pass on something
that's not our own. Um we should use it
at its best for a research assistant or
a conversational partner in terms of a
prompt. And so um I am finding those two
uses helpful even [clears throat] though
I'm much I probably the age that I am
I'm much slower uh to use this than to
be honest the reason I even uh have
looked into these things because the
younger professionals in the
congregation I serve are already uh
embracing it. And so, uh, I realized,
okay, I'm I'm going to have to dive in
here. And so, I have used it, uh, for
questions like, what's the
distinctiveness of Israel's view of love
in comparison to ancient neareastern
religions?
Well, a question like that is an answer
is very helpful. Why is it helpful?
Because um, uh, it shows the
distinctiveness and it gives some
sources that you can then go further
with. The key for me is going further
with the sources
um to see uh if that's you know to the
degree what I'm finding there. But it's
a prompt. I that's like reading a
commentary, reading a good commentary
and someone uh pointed out these
distinctions and I see their footnotes
with their quotes. I prefer the
commentary because I see where the
sources are coming from. But um but it
is helpful in that way. Uh yeah, those
are some thoughts. Yeah. No, that's
that's good food for thought and adding
a bit of a framework.
>> Well, Zach, I appreciate uh your
presentation for a few reasons. The
emphasis on wisdom with that, the
emphasis on Jesus and even um as you're
recovering the role of preacher as sage
and how questions may play into that as
that helps us be present, curious, and
so forth. Um, and I can even just see
perhaps one of the answers to my
question would be about um the curiosity
that you would have with the text would
help you be more present um with the
Lord, attentive to the spirit, with
people. But um I would actually just I
would love to hear further from you just
how your own preaching has changed due
to this emphasis on wisdom over the past
decade or so.
Yeah, that's a great question. Uh,
people who have known me uh preach back
then and now let me know let me know the
change changes they see and that's been
helpful to me. You know, we it's not
always easy to see in ourselves. Um, one
one significant change is tone and
posture.
And so, um,
uh, wisdom from above, I I, um, I
probably, you know, a quick way to say
it would be wisdom from above, wisdom
from below. Wisdom from above in James 3
is, um, pure, peaceable, gentle,
impartial, open to reason, sincere. You
know, um, Paul's way of talking
similarly, the fruit of the spirit,
love, joy, peace, patience, kindness.
Um, I
a more a greater conviction
that those passages of scripture are as
equally authoritative as any verse on
justification by faith alone. And so
that I am I the Lord's servant Paul says
to Timothy uh must not be quarrelome but
gently instruct those who oppose him. So
uh I think maybe I I would have hit
instruction without the gentleness.
>> I think another an opposite problem is
gentleness without instructing those who
oppose us.
But um another another place is first 1
Thessalonians 5:14 admonish the idol. Uh
encourage the faint-hearted, help the
weak, be patient with them all.
>> So I'm not going to admonish the
faint-hearted or the weak. M
>> I'm not going to encourage uh the idol,
but even if I'm uh admonishing the idol,
I must be patient.
>> And even if I'm encouraging the
faint-hearted, I must do so patiently.
And um and I think that is a a
significant change. That's not just
being nice.
um to to it is revealing the character
of Jesus, the character of God to a
person. And it takes profound courage
and strength to stand in the presence of
someone who's opposing you and gently
instruct them. Remain quick to listen,
slow to speak, slow to anger. It is the
thing that distinguishes wisdom from
above from wisdom from below. And uh
that's one maj that's a significant
change that's I I pray continues to grow
in me. Another significant change would
be um
I no longer think I have to solve the
issue in one sermon.
So that's a real change and and some
folks have had a real problem with that
to be honest. Uh it's a critique
um to to to that person what is true and
what to do. There's we already know the
truth. Say it, clarify it. Uh I I hardly
agree with that. It's just that if I'm
talking to a person who uh was abused by
their youth pastor and the youth pastor
is in prison and that person has just
risked with church for the first time in
four years.
uh to give them the best chance of
hearing
this this truth is going to is going to
need uh the ability to recognize this is
not a Judaizer.
>> This is not a hard-hearted covenant
breaker. This is someone who's been s
against. And yes, uh there will be sin
in this person's life, too, of course,
but they've been sinned against. And um
I think that's a change. I would not
necessarily have kept that person in
view earlier on the way I hope I hope
I'm learning to do now. Yeah.
>> No, I I appreciate that. Uh even from
your
story that you gave about a daughter
coming to her parents and saying that
I'm interested in witchcraft. But just
to reflect on the tone, it's just like
hey that's wrong. Like you need to
repent. But I can see t the change in
tone being very evident there and in
addition to the other examples as you're
thinking. So I appreciate that. Um it's
it's a joy when you have other people
say come to you and say hey I've you're
growing here and I know there's a
there's a little defensiveness where
it's like oh you're critiquing the
fiveyear-old me over there. It's like
five years ago. Um so I appreciate that
truly. Um, but a second question I was
having is as we're as you're thinking
about Jesus coming alongside,
commending, but also offending, perhaps
even rebuking. Um, but then there's this
invitation. Like I think about my own
culture and context. I'm in a very
progressive community and it's a college
town. It's a party town. um party
university and like I'm I want to think
further just more about the specific
ways that Jesus can resonate with our
culture. um because that can be easy to
miss. But like I and so it's really a
question like what are some ways that
you see that within your own culture and
context of Jesus resonating with culture
in way
how how that's the case like I think
about one example for for myself um like
having being near a college campus and
seeing the party culture well Jesus's
first ministry
excuse me first miracle is actually for
a party and so like seeing some
similarity there and that's kind of like
what I'm going at because I know that
can be hard to miss but what are some
things that you see within your own
context
>> yeah I um that's such a good question
and much of the
maybe one quick way to say it is
anything a any any good thing a human
being longs for
uh they do so because they were created
in the image of God and uh and it was
the it was the Lord himself who
was meant to satisfy that longing
and that includes I mean I'm with I I
follow the line of thinking here of
folks like GK Chesterton and others that
includes
uh the longing for a good thing and
trying to find it badly, you know,
looking for it in all the wrong ways and
places.
And um so there there there certainly
can be an out-and-out hedenist on a
college campus. There is no point.
There's cynic hedenism. We're all going
to die. Paul Paul affirms that. If Jesus
didn't rise from the dead, what else is
there to do? We should we should get
drunk, have sex, and be married as long
as we can. Like the Bible already gives
language for that. Um, that is that is a
a rational response to a godless world.
But what if what if
God is here?
Uh, and and now this um there are some
folks who are longing for intimacy.
They're longing for love. They're
longing for belonging. They're longing
for friendship. They're longing for a
sense of meaning. and they're pursuing
it through, you know, the party culture.
Um, the thing they're pursuing, we
those good things beneath that, we can
affirm. You were made for intimacy. You
were made
a party. We We were made to celebrate uh
uh we were made to be able to laugh
together and feel at home together and
be at ease together. that that's a
creation. We I I I think of this, you
know, if we borrow Jerem Bars's phrase,
this is an echo of Eden. This is these
are uh things that we can't help because
we're made in the image of God. and uh
and what and um and so I think being
able to affirm those things, paying
attention, being able to affirm them is
really important uh because it touches
the humanity of a person that they're
they're a creature, a human creature
before God. And so Paul does this
in Acts 17 um not Acts 17, Acts 14. We
you know we know Acts 17 where he quotes
the philosophers and the poets. But in
Acts 14
uh Paul identifies their inner feelings
of gladness
and joy with uh good work and rainy
seasons and the fruitfulness of their
labor. And the Greek word there is
martyr. You know uh these this joy of
soul is a martyr. it is the testifier
from God. Um and so in that in that case
in Ephesians in uh Acts 14 Paul appeals
to their the inner experience of good
among other than Christian people and he
says that inex that inner experience of
good
I want to tell you where that comes
from. You know it's bearing witness
about the God I want to tell you about.
And so, um, there's a lot more to say
here. I think we've had good help from
our from theologians, uh, like John
Calvin or more recent preachers like Tim
Keller who've reminded us of common
grace. uh but the scripture itself um
when you're in the wisdom literature
itself uh you know the the strength of
something like Ecclesiastes or um is
it's it's identifying earthy goods.
There's nothing better than to enjoy
your food and your drink uh your lot and
life the things given you and it's sort
of hearkening back to these edenic goods
that um haven't quit uh they will be
restored and made in their fullness you
know in the new kingdom. So
maybe there's some things in what I'm
sharing that can be of help for further
thought. I'm with you. I think you're
I'm I'm following with you, you know,
what you're thinking about with those
young people on the college campus.
>> Well, I appreciate it. So, thank you
very much. Appreciate your answers.
>> Friends, this has been a rich
conversation. Thank you, Zach. As as we
bring it to a close, I just want to say
um yeah, it thank you all for your
questions and Zach, thank you for your
your thoughts and your um openness and
and your wisdom.
>> Oh, thank you. I uh it's been very good
to be with you. I uh appreciate the
questions because they help me as well
uh for the local pastoral work here. So
thanks so much everybody.